<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Exercise 1: first steps with Oxygen</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI</publisher>
        <availability>
          <p>Freely available for use and derivative works under a Creative Commons Attribution
            license.</p>
        </availability>
        <date>2008-07-07</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Some bits may be lifted from previous talks/workshops by the TEI Community and certainly
          from the TEI P5 1.0 Release of the Guidelines.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>$LastChangedDate: 2008-07-21 11:56:54 +0100 (Mon, 21 Jul 2008) $.</date>
        <name>$LastChangedBy: rahtz $</name>
        <note>$LastChangedRevision: 3096 $</note>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
<div>
<head>First steps with Oxygen</head>
<p>In this first exercise you will learn how to use Oxygen to
<list>
<item>create a new XML document</item>
<item>add markup to a document</item>
<item>keep your document well-formed</item>
<item>display and edit your document without seeing tags</item>
</list>
</p>
</div>

<div><head>Creating a new document</head>
<p>Start up Oxygen, and click the New Document icon at top left (or
select New Document from the File menu, or type CTRL-N.) to display
the New dialog.</p>
<p> <graphic url="../Graphics/oxy-new-1.png"/></p>
<p>Select the default XML option, and press OK.</p>

<p>In the "Create an XML Document" dialog, <emph>uncheck</emph> the
tick box <val>Use a DTD or a schema</val>, since we don't yet have a
schema.</p>
<p> <graphic url="../Graphics/oxy-new-2.png" width="5in"/></p>
<p> Press OK to continue.</p>

<p>Oxygen opens a blank document, containing just the XML declaration
at the start. As you start typing in XML, notice how hard Oxygen tries
to make your document well-formed.</p>

<p><list>
<item>type in <code>&lt;div type="</code> and pause</item>
<item>notice that Oxygen supplies the closing quote for you</item>
<item>continue typing <code>verse</code> and move the cursor
<emph>after</emph> the closing quote (use an arrow key)</item>
<item>Type the closing <code>&gt;</code> and note that Oxygen
immediately supplies the closing <code>&lt;/div></code> for you. Press
the RETURN key</item>
</list>
</p>
</div>

<div><head>Adding text to a document</head>
<p>Your document should now look like this:</p>
<p><graphic url="../Graphics/oxy-new-3.png" width="6in"/></p>
<list>
<item>Select File from the Document menu</item>
<item> Select Insert File from the
submenu that opens.</item>
<item>Navigate to the file <ident>pushkin.txt</ident> in your working
directory (or <ref target="Resources/pushkin.txt">download it</ref>) and insert it into
your document.</item>
</list>
<p>This is a plain text version of a famous poem by Pushkin. 
<!--<item>Navigate to the file <ident>progress.txt</ident in your working
directory (or <ref target="Resources/progress.txt">download it</ref>) and insert it into
your document.</item>
</list>
<p>This is a plain text version of the poem at the start of our sample
Punch issue. -->
In the rest of this exercise we will add some minimal
tagging.</p>
</div>

<div><head>Tagging bits of a document</head>
<list>
<item>With the mouse, select the word <q>K * * *</q> <!--<q>PROGRESS</q>--> at the start of the
text. </item>
<item>Press CTRL-E (or select XML Refactoring/Surround with Tag from
the Document menu).</item>
<item>Type the name of the tag you want to use into the popup: this is
a heading, so type <code>head</code> and press OK</item>
</list>
<p><graphic width="6in" url="../Graphics/oxy-new-4-ru.png"/></p>
<!--<p>Repeat the process for the whole of the paragraph in square
brackets: this time, tag it as a <gi>p</gi>.</p>-->
</div>

<div><head>Tagging the poem</head>
<p>We will tag the poem proper using <gi>lg</gi> to enclose each
stanza, and <gi>l</gi> to enclose each   <gi>l</gi>.</p>
<list>
<item>Try typing the sequence <gi>lg</gi><gi>l</gi> at the start of
the first line. Delete the unwanted <gi>/l></gi> and <gi>/lg</gi> tags
inserted by Oxygen. </item>
<item>Put the cursor at the end of the first <emph>stanza</emph>
(after the word <!--<q>sticks</q>--><q>красоты.</q>) and type &lt;</item>
<item>A small menu opens, showing that you can enter a closing-tag (to
close the <gi>l</gi>
element) here. Select it. </item>
<item>Type another &lt; and the same menu appears: but note that this
time the closing-tag to be inserted is a <gi>/lg</gi>. Select this,
and the document becomes valid -- no red lines visible.</item>
<item>What will happen if you repeat the process, do you think? Try it
and see!</item>
</list>
</div>

<div><head>Tagging the poem properly</head>
<p>Although well-formed our tagging is not very honest. We have a
single <gi>l</gi> element containing several lines, and lots of
stanzas which are not tagged as anything at all. If we were validating
this document against a schema we'd be in trouble.</p>
<list>
<item>put the cursor at the end of the first line (after
<q>мгновенье:</q>)</item>
<item>select XML Refactoring/Split Element from the
Document menu.</item>
</list>
<p>This closes the current <gi>l</gi> and immediately opens a new one,
so that our document remains valid. We just need to repeat this
process for each line. We could do that by repeating what we just
did. Or, more simply perhaps, we could add the XML Document Refactoring
toolbar, which would provide a single button to do the job. </p>
<p>We'll do something even simpler.  Use the mouse
to select the sequence of characters you just inserted
(<code>&lt;/l>&lt;l></code>); copy it with CTRL-C; move the cursor to
the end of the next line; paste it with CTRL-V. Repeat this for each
line in the stanza, except the last one of course.</p>
</div>

<div><head>Tagging another way</head>

<p>Some people just don't like tags. Fortunately, Oxygen also has a <soCalled>tag
free</soCalled> editing mode: it works by displaying
parts of the text which are tagged in different ways in different
styles. We specify the style for each tag by means of a
<term>stylesheet</term> associated with the document.</p>
<list>
<item>Select XML Document/Associate XSLT/CSS Stylesheet from the
Document menu (or click the appropriate button if you can find it). In
the Associate dialog, navigate to the file <ident>pushkin.css</ident>
in your working directory (or <ref target="Resources/pushkin.css">download
it</ref>) and select it. Observe that a new processing instruction is added at
the start of your document.</item>
<item>At the bottom of the editing window, you see a choice of Mode
displays: Text (the default), Grid, and Author. Select the
last. Observe that the display changes and a new Menu option (Author)
is now available. Select this and observe the effect of the various
command options on it.</item>
<item>Choose  <code>No Tags</code> for the next part of this exercise.</item>
</list>
<p><graphic width="6in" url="../Graphics/oxy-new-5-ru.png"/></p>
</div>

<div><head>Quick splitting</head>
<list>
<item>Use the mouse to select the the rest of the poem (from the start
of the second stanza to the end. <!--word <q>The</q> to
the word <q>shrink</q>) excluding the name
<q>Evoe</q> at the end.--></item>
<item>Use CTRL-E to tag this all as a single <gi>lg</gi>.</item>
<item>Select the same stretch of text again and tag it as a single
<gi>l</gi> in the same way.</item>
<item>Now place the cursor at the end of the first line of the second
stanza (after <q>безнадежной</q><!--,around</q>-->). Press RETURN. A menu offers you the choice of
splitting the <g>l</g> element. Press RETURN again.</item>
<item>Move on to the next line (after <q>banks</q>) and repeat. Repeat for
each subsequent line in the poem.</item>
<item>To split the stanzas, put the cursor at the end of the last line
of the stanza, and use the right arrow key to move it between the
invisible tags (or switch back to Text mode). You should then be able
to split the stanzas in exactly the same way.</item>
<item>You can also experiment with other ways of splitting the text,
of course. If you get into a mess, use CTRL-Z to undo the last change
you made. Remember you can switch between Author and Text views as
much as you like.</item>
<!--<item>Finally, tag the name of the author of the poem (<q>Evoe</q>) using
the <gi>signed</gi> element.</item>-->
</list>
</div>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
