<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Exercise 2: using a schema with Oxygen</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI</publisher>
        <availability>
          <p>Freely available for use and derivative works under a Creative Commons Attribution
            license.</p>
        </availability>
        <date>2008-07-07</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Some bits may be lifted from previous talks/workshops by the TEI Community and certainly
          from the TEI P5 1.0 Release of the Guidelines.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>$LastChangedDate: 2008-07-21 11:56:54 +0100 (Mon, 21 Jul 2008) $.</date>
        <name>$LastChangedBy: rahtz $</name>
        <note>$LastChangedRevision: 3096 $</note>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
<div>
<head>Using a TEI schema</head>
<p>In this  exercise you will learn 
<list>
<item>how to make a valid TEI document, using an Oxygen template</item>
<item>how to use the <hi>Roma</hi> web application to make a TEI
schema</item>
</list>
</p>

<div><head>Using an Oxygen Template</head>
<p>In the first exercise, we made a well-formed document, but we did
not try to make one which conformed to any schema. </p>
<p>Oxygen comes with predefined <term>templates</term> for a large
number of commonly used schemas, including TEI. We'll use one of these
to create a simple TEI Header for the poem we tagged yesterday.</p>
<p>Start up Oxygen. You will see that the documents you were working
on previously are still there. We will start however by making a new
document.<list type="ordered">
<item><p>As before, click the New Document icon at top left (or
select New Document from the File menu, or type CTRL-N.) to display
the New dialog. This time, however, select the <ident>from
Templates</ident> tab</p>
<p>
<graphic width="5in"  url="../Graphics/oxy-newtemp-1.png"/> </p>
<p>Scroll down the
list to select TEI P5 - Lite. Press OK.</p></item>
<item><p>A new editing window opens, with the basic parts of a valid TEI
header already present.</p>
<p><graphic width="5in" 
url="../Graphics/oxy-newtemp-2.png"/>. </p><p> Replace the English text
content with some appropriate Russian text for the title, publication
statement, and source description for your digital edition of the
Pushkin poem.</p></item>
<item>You need to replace the text <code><![CDATA[<p>Some text here.</p>]]></code>
inside the <gi>text</gi> element that follows the
<gi>teiHeader</gi> with the contents of the file you
prepared earlier. The easiest way is to cut-and-paste: 
<list>
<item>Click on the tab containing the window in which you edited the
Pushkin poem (it should be labelled <ident>pushkin.xml</ident>)</item>
<item>Use the mouse to select the
whole of the <gi>div type="poem"</gi> element</item>
<item>Press CTRL-c (or select Copy from the Edit menu)</item>
<item>Now click on the tab for the file you just created (it's probably
labelled <ident>untitled.xml</ident> unless you saved it) </item>
<item>Select the text <code><![CDATA[<p>Some text here.</p>]]></code>
with the mouse and press CTRL-v (or select Paste from the Edit menu)
to replace it with the Pushkin poem</item>
</list></item>
<item>Is the poem valid? What do you need to do to make it
valid?</item>
<item>Now go back to your <gi>teiHeader</gi>. We will add a
<gi>revisionDesc</gi> element to show when the document was completed.

<list>
<item>Use the mouse to place the cursor immediately after the
closing-tag <gi>/fileDesc</gi></item>
<item><p>Type the &lt; character and observe that Oxygen shows you only  the
elements that are valid at this point together with a brief description of
each</p><p><graphic width="5in"  url="../Graphics/oxy-elem.png"/></p></item>
<item>Use the arrow key to step down to the one you want to insert:
<gi>revisionDesc</gi> and press RETURN</item>
<item>The cursor stays inside the start-tag for <gi>revisionDesc</gi>
in case you want to add some attributes; since we don't want to, press
the right arrow key to move immediately before the end-tag, and type
in a &lt; again.</item>
<item>You can enter a <gi>list</gi> or a <gi>change</gi>; we suggest
the latter.</item>
<item>This time, with the cursor inside the start-tag for
<gi>change</gi>, press the space bar.</item>
<item><p>A long list of the available attributes for this element
appears. Scroll down it to select <ident>when</ident>, and press
Return. </p>
<p><graphic width="5in"  url="../Graphics/oxy-attr.png"/></p></item>
<item>Enter today's date in the form <code>YYYY-MM-DD</code> as the
value for this attribute. Note
what happens if you try to supply an invalid date (such as the 32nd of
August). </item>
<item>We suggest you enter some text such as <q>first valid TEI
version</q> as content for the <gi>change</gi> element.</item></list></item>
<item>Experiment to see what other elements are available at different
points in your document, if you like.</item>
<item>Click on the Author button at the bottom of the screen to see
your completed document. Remember to save it!</item>
</list>
</p>
</div>

<div><head>Making a TEI Schema</head>
<p>In the previous exercise, we used a pre-defined TEI schema called
TEI Lite. This schema has all you need for marking up most kinds of
TEI documents -- but quite a lot more than most people want. You can
use the web application Roma to make any kind of TEI schema, simple or
complex. We'll start with a very simple one.
<list type="ordered">
<item>Open <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/Roma/"/> using any web browser </item>
<item><p>Click the radio button next to "Create Customization from
Template". Use the default option "Absolutely Bare".</p>
<p><graphic width="5in"  url="../Graphics/roma-bare.png"/>)</p></item>
<item>Press the big red button at bottom left</item>
<item><p>Roma shows you information about the schema you are about to
create. </p>
<p><graphic width="5in"  url="../Graphics/roma-param.png"/></p></item>
<item><p>Roma has many facilities, accessed by means of the buttons
across the  top of the screen. You can customize the interface
language as well. If you'd rather see things in Russian, click the
radio button next to "Russian", and then press the big red button at
bottom left again.</p>
<p> <graphic width="5in"  url="../Graphics/roma-param-ru.png"/></p></item>
<item>For now, we just want a schema. Press the button that says
<ident>Schema</ident> (cxema) </item>
<item><p>You have a choice of schema languages: choose the default (Relax
NG schema (compact syntax), and press the big red button at
bottom left again. </p><p><graphic width="5in"  url="../Graphics/roma-rnc.png"/></p></item>
<item>Roma will send you a file <ident>tei_bare.rnc</ident>; save it
in your working directory for the next part of the exercise. </item>
</list>
</p>

</div>


<div><head>Marking up Mr Punch</head>

<p>For the rest of this exercise, we'd like you to try marking up a
page from Punch. To help you, we've prepared the following files, all
of which you should be able to find in your Working Directory:
<list>
<item>the directory <ident>Punch/Pages</ident> contains graphic images
of each page of the issue, called things like
<ident>147_001.jpg</ident> (for page one)</item>
<item>the directory <ident>Punch/Text</ident> contains plain text for
each page, called things like <ident>page2.txt</ident> (for page 2)</item>
<item>the file <ident>XML/punchHdr.xml</ident> contains a sample TEI
Header for you to modify, or prefix to your document.</item>
<item>the directory <ident>XML/Graphics</ident> contains image files
for all the illustrations in the issue, called things like
<ident>003.png</ident> for the illustration  on page 3.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Start by choosing the page you want to work on. Some are very easy
-- and some are less so!</p>
<p>Open Oxygen again, and make a New document, as before. This time
however, when you see the <title>Create an XML Document</title>
dialogue, make sure that the checkbox <title>Use a DTD or
Schema</title> is checked. </p>
<p>Select the <ident>Relax NG</ident> tab, and then navigate to
wherever you have saved the tei_bare.rnc file which Roma made for you
in the previous exercise. Use this as your schema.</p>
<p>Using the techniques you've already learned you should find it easy
to...
<list>
<item>insert the default TEI Header at the start of your new
document</item>
<item>find out what elements this schema offers you to mark up the
text</item>
<item>select the elements you want, and mark up stretches of text with them.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>How far can you get with your chosen page? Since the bare_bones
schema really only offers paragraphs and lists, don't be too
discouraged if the answer is <q>not very!</q></p>
<p>We need to modify the schema to include more elements. To do this,
we will return to Roma and discover more about what it offers.</p>
</div>
<div><head>A more ambitious schema</head>
<p>In this part of the exercise, we will build a <soCalled>less
bare</soCalled> version of the tei_bare schema, by adding to it some
elements we need to mark up the Punch texts.</p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>Start up Roma and select the Bare Bones customization as
before.</item>
<item><p>Select the <ident>Modules</ident> (moduli) tab: you will see a
list of available modules on the left, and the modules selected on the
right. </p><p><graphic width="5in"  url="../Graphics/roma-1-ru.png"/>) </p></item>
<item>Click on the word <code>add</code> (<code>Добавление</code>) next to the word 
<ident>graphics</ident> on the left. This will add that module
to the list on the right.</item>
<item>Now we need to see what elements are being used from each of
the modules in our schema. Start by clicking on the word
<code>core</code> in the list on the right.</item>
<item>A long list of element names appears. You can:
<list>
<item>indicate whether the element is to be included (the Включить
button is selected) or
excluded (the Исключить button is selected)</item>
<item>change the spelling of the element's name (not
recommended!)</item>
<item>use the question mark button to read a formal definition of this
element in the online TEI Guidelines</item>
<item>... or review the brief description of it</item>
<item>and you can also review the attributes available for this
element by clicking on <code>Изменение атрибутов
</code></item></list>
<p><graphic width="5in"  url="../Graphics/roma-elements.png"/></p></item>
<item>We suggest that, for  basic markup of a Punch page, you'll
need to add at least the elements <gi>bibl</gi>, <gi>cit</gi>, <gi>graphic</gi>, <gi>hi</gi>, <gi>l</gi>,
<gi>lg</gi>, <gi>name</gi>, <gi>pb</gi>, <gi>q</gi>, <gi>sp</gi>,
<gi>speaker</gi> and <gi>stage</gi>. But feel free to explore, and add
others! </item>
<item>When you're done, click the "Submit Query" button at bottom
left, and the schema will be updated with your selection. Then press
the <ident>Back</ident> button at top left to return to the modules
page. </item>
<item>Review the elements provided by the <ident>figures</ident>
module which you added to the schema earlier. You will see that this
adds only a few elements: you may however want to remove the <gi>formula</gi>
element.</item>
<item>When you are happy with your selection, click on the Schema
button to generate a schema as before.</item>
<item>Save the schema generated as an RNC file, as before.</item>
<item>You can also generate a manual for your colleagues: click on
Documentation.</item>
</list>

<p>Now it's over to you! Go back to Oxygen and see if you can improve
on the tagging of the document you were working on by using your new
schema.</p>
<p>To tell Oxygen to use your new schema, rather than <ident>teibare</ident>, proceed
as follows:
<list>
<item>Remove the processing instruction which Oxygen inserted at the
head of your document: it probably looks like this:
<code>&lt;?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_bare.rng"
type="xml"?></code>
</item>
<item>Select "Associate Schema" on the "XML Document" submenu of the
"Document" menu.
<p><graphic width="5in"  url="../Graphics/oxy-assoc.png"/></p>
</item>
<item>Specify the file in which you saved the schema that Roma
generated for you.</item>
</list>
</p>
</div>
</div>    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
